<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Seth W. Musser on Seth W. Musser</title>
    <link>https://swmusser.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Seth W. Musser on Seth W. Musser</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Selected Publications</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/publications_selected/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/publications_selected/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flying in a Superfluid</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/post/superfluid-flight/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/post/superfluid-flight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Physical Review Letters recently published research I did as an undergraduate in the Irvine lab, &lt;a href=&#34;https://swmusser.com/publication/superfluid-flying/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Starting Flow Past an Airfoil and its Acquired Lift in a Superfluid&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I wanted to write a blog post about it, and since flying in a superfluid strikes me as something that might be interesting to the broader physics community I checked &lt;a href=&#34;https://physics.stackexchange.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;physics.stackexchange.com&lt;/a&gt;. To my pleasant surprise I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/111659/would-an-airplane-flying-through-superfluid-helium-experience-lift-and-drag/126286&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;not one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/46131/does-a-wing-in-a-potential-flow-have-lift&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;but two&lt;/a&gt; questions related to flight in a superfluid. Unfortunately, the top voted answers on these questions assert: &amp;ldquo;viscosity is necessary in order for the wing to generate lift&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;lift cannot exist without viscosity&amp;rdquo;, respectively. Our paper linked above directly shows that this is in fact not true. Indeed, this misconception provides a great starting point to understanding flight in general, and flight in a superfluid specifically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussion of airfoils in two dimensions usually begins by treating fluid around the foil as ideal, i.e. incompressible (unable to be compressed) and inviscid (free of any internal &amp;ldquo;friction&amp;rdquo; that might dissipate energy). This is a pretty good approximation for most scenarios and it has the benefit of allowing for the flow field around a special type of airfoil, the Joukowski airfoil, to be exactly solved. The details involve a nice application of complex analysis, and can be found in D. J. Acheson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Elementary-Dynamics-Applied-Mathematics-Computing/dp/0198596790&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elementary Fluid Dynamics&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The upshot is that once a foil&amp;rsquo;s length, width, speed, and angle of attack are specified you can get a solution which is not just exact, but almost unique. The one ambiguity is that any solution can have arbitrary &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circulation_(fluid_dynamics)&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;circulation&lt;/a&gt; added to the foil and still satisfy the Euler equtions describing incompressible and inviscid fluid flow. One possible flow field with zero circulation is shown below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://swmusser.github.io/img/superfluid-flying/streamlines_nocirc.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;streamlines&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ambiguity around circulation is a pretty important ambiguity though! The &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutta%E2%80%93Joukowski_theorem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kutta-Joukowski theorem&lt;/a&gt; shows that the lift around any airfoil in a two dimensional flow is proportional to the circulation around it. No circulation, no flight. The foil above would never get off the ground. Given that we know real wings do in fact fly, how do they choose a value of circulation that allows them to do so? In &lt;em&gt;Elementary Fluid Dynamics&lt;/em&gt; Acheson points out that for all circulations but one, called the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kutta_condition&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Kutta-Joukowski circulation&lt;/a&gt;, the ideal fluid velocity is infinite at the tail of the foil. This suggests that the foil chooses the perfect circulation to avoid this unphysical divergence. However, the real story is a little more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the commenters at physics StackExchange point out, real foils take advantage of non-zero viscosity to choose the perfect circulation. The non-zero, albeit small, viscosity of both air and water means that these fluids get &amp;ldquo;stuck&amp;rdquo; to the surface of a real airfoil. The flow far away from the foil is not altered by the enforcement of this no-slip condition, but close to the foil a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boundary_layer&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;boundary layer&lt;/a&gt; is established where the flow interpolates from zero velocity to its ideal value. In particular this means that the velocity at the tail is no longer infinite for &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; circulation in a viscous fluid. However, it is still very large for all circulations but the Kutta-Joukowski circulation. This creates a pressure gradient that actually pulls the boundary layers off of the foil and into a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starting_vortex&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;starting vortex&lt;/a&gt; when the foil is quickly accelerated from rest to some non-zero velocity. The starting vortex has the negative of the Kutta-Joukowski circulation which, by helicity conservation, gives the foil the Kutta-Joukowski circulation; exactly the value predicted by the naive ideal fluid analysis. A great image of this starting vortex is shown below, courtesy of the National Committee for Fluid Mechanics Films.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://swmusser.github.io/img/superfluid-flying/start_vort.png&#34; alt=&#34;startingvortex&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus lift generation in a viscous fluid can thus be thought of in the following steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Viscosity establishes boundary layers, which are then pulled off due to pressure gradients into a starting vortex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) This starting vortex imparts the equal and opposite circulation onto the foil itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) The foil&amp;rsquo;s circulation provides lift via the Kutta-Joukowski theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can lift every be generated if we remove 1), the ability of viscosity to form a starting vortex? Again the commenters at physics StackExchange are correct that in the ideal theory, that is the theory of incompressible and inviscid fluid flow, there is no physical process which enforces that the foil must have the Kutta-Joukowski circulation. Superfluids&amp;hellip;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting Flow Past an Airfoil and its Acquired Lift in a Superfluid</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/publication/superfluid-flying/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/publication/superfluid-flying/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flying in a superfluid: starting flow past an airfoil</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/superfluid-flight/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Aug 2019 08:56:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/superfluid-flight/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Physics and Mathematics Instruction</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/post/physics-instruction/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/post/physics-instruction/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In many of the physics courses I&amp;rsquo;ve taken in my undergraduate and graduate years &lt;em&gt;The Feynman Lectures on Physics&lt;/em&gt; have been presented as the gold standard when it comes to physics instruction. They certainly left their impact on me; Feynman&amp;rsquo;s discussion of thermodynamics as illustrated by the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brownian_ratchet&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Brownian ratchet&lt;/a&gt; is a fresh way to approach the subject and I find myself returning to it from time to time. As with this example, much of Feyman&amp;rsquo;s technique relied on rebuilding a subject&amp;rsquo;s instruction from the ground up, attempting to present every subject with maximum appeal to intuition. That approach worked well for him in part because he was a genius and in part because he &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Feynman#Pedagogy&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;devoted a lot of time to preparing the lectures&lt;/a&gt;. This makes Feynman&amp;rsquo;s method of instruction nigh on impossible to replicate by your average physicist, though some do try with varying success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better model for your average physics instructor is, in my view, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/teaching.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Tong&amp;rsquo;s lecture notes&lt;/a&gt;. I think his real success is not necessarily in rebuilding entire subjects, but rather in presenting them in a way that is easily digestible by a motivated student. Presenting physics in this way is a teachable skill, and relies on a basic algorithmic lesson structure. The basic format is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Motivating Example: begin with a motivating example. Fully explore the example at the level of students&amp;rsquo; current understanding. A good example will be simple, perhaps even one that students have encountered before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) General Theory: introduce the theory you want to teach the students about. Whenever possible, tie it back to the motivating example in order to provide grounding and sanity checks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Demonstrate Value: use the general theory you&amp;rsquo;ve built up to analyze other more difficult systems. This demonstrates the utility of what you&amp;rsquo;ve taught to students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see Tong use this approach in his lecture notes on &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/sft/sft.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Statistical Field Theory&lt;/a&gt; (SFT). His goal is to teach students about renormalization. He begins with the Ising Model, the simple model many advanced undergraduates are already familiar with. Then for almost the next hundred pages he introduces crucial concepts of SFT, all linked back to the Ising Model. Eventually he builds to renormalization and the renormalization group, but with all path integrals being done for the Ising Model. Since he has spent significant time building students&amp;rsquo; intuitions about the model it is much easier to follow these sometimes lengthy calculations. Finally, in the last section of his notes he turns to the more difficult $ O(N) $ models, applying the tools of renormalization that he carefully built using the Ising Model. He finishes with a fascinating discussion of the Kosterlitz-Thouless transition, hinting at topological phase transitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example of this approach comes from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/dbs26/AQFT.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Skinner&amp;rsquo;s lecture notes&lt;/a&gt; on Quantum Field Theory (QFT). In order to introduce the formalism of the path integral Skinner begins with QFT in zero dimensions, his motivating example. In zero dimensions a real valued field is just a single real number, and the space of all field configurations is just $ \mathbb{R} $. This means that the path integrals are just ordinary integrals, something all students have seen before. Skinner then uses this motivating example to demonstrate how integrating out higher energy fields can generate all interactions allowed by symmetry. This is a hugely important concept in QFT, and it was one that seemed really mysterious to me when I first encountered it. I had the misconception that the generation of all these extra terms was something that was coming from the (to me) inaccessible path integral. When I took Skinner&amp;rsquo;s class and saw that it was something that would actually arise from a familiar old integral, it not only helped me to understand the general theory of path integrals, but also made it much more accessible to me by tying it back to a simple example I understood well. Skinner then very skillfully used his toy model to illustrate a whole host of other important concepts in QFT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course even though the examples I&amp;rsquo;ve just described were related to field theory, the algorithmic lesson structure outlined above can be hugely useful for any subject in physics and mathematics. If you are teaching middle schoolers about chemistry the motivating example might be more physical, e.g. simply dropping a piece of Sodium into water and watching the reaction unfold. This piques the interest of the students, and makes an explanation of chemical reactions that much easier to understand and to follow. If you are presenting analysis to students for the first time, motivating $ \epsilon-\delta $ proofs with graphs of simple functions like $ f(x)=x $ helps students latch on to why one defines a limit in this way. You can then develop the general theory of limits and finally extend it to complicated examples that are difficult to picture graphically, e.g. perhaps the Weierstrass function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe now that I&amp;rsquo;ve gone through all these examples you find this lecture structure to be obvious. But in my experience it is rarely put to use, or at least used well, in the classroom. I&amp;rsquo;ve seen professors deviate from it many times, for what I would guess are a multitude of reasons: some want to surprise the students with a beautiful proof and fear if they motivate it too much they&amp;rsquo;ll give away the game, some simply cannot look at their subject with the eyes of a newcomer and they focus on small details that to them seem important (but fail to give a clear overarching motivating example), some try to replicate Feynman&amp;rsquo;s pedagogy and fall short, but most are just too busy to think about presenting their topic in this way. Indeed when I was a tutor for the introductory calculus sequence at UChicago I myself fell into all of these traps at various times. However, in spite of the difficulty in structuring one&amp;rsquo;s lessons in this way I think it is worth the effort in order to help students&amp;rsquo; understanding, and I will continue to look to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/tong/teaching.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;David Tong&amp;rsquo;s lecture notes&lt;/a&gt; for inspiration while I put in this effort.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title> &#39;Proving&#39; Euler&#39;s formula to calculus students</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/post/nifty_trick/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/post/nifty_trick/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Back in high school when I took AP Calc BC I encountered integration using partial fractions. Later, while fooling around with the idea I realized I could use it to connect trigonometric functions, imaginary numbers, and the complex exponential. I didn&amp;rsquo;t think much of it at the time, but shortly thereafter I learned of Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula and realized that I had stumbled upon a way to &amp;ldquo;prove&amp;rdquo; this relation using integration techniques familiar to most students of calculus. (While researching the proof for this post I discovered that Johann Bernoulli &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%27s_formula#History&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;nearly completed a similar &amp;ldquo;proof&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; in the 18th century, so the idea was just a new one to me.) Afterwards I demonstrated the idea to my intro calc class at UChicgo, which some of them appreciated. I will reproduce the argument here, as I expect some will find it amusing and may want to show it to their own undergraduate students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As any student of calculus will be familiar with
$$\begin{eqnarray}
\tan^{-1}(x) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \left[\tan^{-1}(y) \right]_0^{x} \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \int_0^{x} \frac{1}{1+y^2} \ \mathrm{d}y.
\end{eqnarray}$$
If we now use the difference of squares to see that $ 1+y^2 = (1+iy)(1-iy) $, then we can split up the integrand into the sum of two fractions using the technique of partial fractions. So therefore:
$$\begin{eqnarray}
\tan^{-1}(x) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \int_0^{x} \frac{1}{1+y^2} \ \mathrm{d}y \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{1}{2}\int_0^{x} \left[\frac{1}{1+iy} + \frac{1}{1-iy}\right] \ \mathrm{d}y \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{i}{2}\left[\ln(1 - iy) - \ln(1 + iy) \right]_0^{x} \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{i}{2}\ln\left(\frac{1-ix}{1+ix}\right).
\end{eqnarray}$$
Our reasoning has been slightly dubious here, namely we&amp;rsquo;ve ignored the multi-valued nature of the complex logarithm. That&amp;rsquo;s probably not a hugely important distinction for those just learning calculus, however, so we forge onward. This is the relation that I originally derived while fooling around with partial fractions. Clearly it contains a connection between trigonometric functions, imaginary numbers, and the complex exponential (by way of the complex logarithm). However, in order to get to Euler&amp;rsquo;s formula we&amp;rsquo;ll need to do a bit of algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s define $ \theta \equiv \tan^{-1}(x) $, note that $ \theta \in (-\pi,\pi] $ just as we would want from an angle. Then using the relation we derived above, we see
$$\begin{eqnarray}
e^{i\theta} &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \exp\left(-\frac{1}{2}\ln\left(\frac{1-ix}{1+ix}\right)\right) \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \sqrt{\frac{1+ix}{1-ix}} \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \sqrt{\frac{(1+ix)^2}{(1-ix)(1+ix)}} \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{1+ix}{\sqrt{1+x^2}} \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \frac{1+i\tan(\theta)}{\sqrt{1+\tan^2(\theta)}} \ \text{ since } x=\tan(\theta) \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \cos(\theta)[1+i\tan(\theta)] \ \text{ since } 1+\tan^2(\theta) = \sec^2(\theta) \\&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;amp;=&amp;amp; \cos(\theta) + i \sin(\theta).
\end{eqnarray}$$
We have thus arrived at the Euler formula, though we played it fast and loose with our algebra here with regards to the complex square root and logarithm. This derivation is, in my opinion, a much more interesting one than comparing the power series of the two sides. It also provides a great payoff for students of calculus to prove, with techniques familiar to them, that $ i^i = \exp(i\pi/2)^i = e^{-\pi/2} $!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Particle Vortex Duality: A Review</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/particle-vortex/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 08:56:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/particle-vortex/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Geometry with Applications to the Hamiltonian Formulation of Inviscid Fluid Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/poisson-geometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jul 2018 08:56:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/poisson-geometry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vortex Nucleation in Superfluids</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/vortex-nucleation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jul 2018 16:00:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/talk/vortex-nucleation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Particle Vortex Essay</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/particle-vortex-essay/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2018 09:59:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/particle-vortex-essay/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weyl&#39;s Law</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/weyl-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2016 10:22:15 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/weyl-law/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poisson Geometry</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/poisson-geometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 11:02:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/poisson-geometry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weakly Nonlinear Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/weakly-nonlinear-oscillations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2014 11:05:44 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://swmusser.github.io/writing/weakly-nonlinear-oscillations/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
